# Jesse Pepijn Geerts

jessegeerts@gmail.com | +44 7534 845 455 | https://jessegeerts.github.io | LinkedIn: jesse-geerts-a4b923bb

## **About**

Computational cognitive neuroscientist and AI researcher with 8+ years of experience in scientific research, specializing in cognitive science, neuroscience, and machine learning. My current research focuses on mechanistic interpretability, specifically the generalization properties of foundation models (LLMs). I have extensive experience designing and running machine learning experiments (PyTorch, JAX), human behavioral experiments, and combining both to adjudicate between different cognitive hypotheses. I have a strong track record of disseminating findings through publications in peer-reviewed journals and conferences ranging from cognitive science (Psychological Review) and neuroscience (Cosyne) to machine learning (ICLR). I am experienced in mentoring PhD and Master's students, teaching undergraduate, Master's, and PhD courses, and lecturing at summer schools.

# Experience

#### Research Fellow | Computational Neuroscience Lab, Imperial | January 2024 - Present

- Conducted research on **AI interpretability**, focusing on circuit mechanisms of generalization ability in transformer models.
- Setting up and leading collaborative project between Imperial, Columbia University and DeepMind on understanding relational reasoning and chain-of-thought prompting in **foundation models**.
- Developed **Deep Reinforcement Learning** model of motor learning explaining striatal and cortical neural manifolds.
- **Mentoring** of MSc thesis on deep self-supervised learning, lecturer in neural dynamics MSc course at Imperial and Neuroinformatics course at SWC.
- Invited lecturer on Reinforcement Learning at NeuroAI summerschool in Amsterdam.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher | Space & Memory Lab, UCL | March 2021 – September 2023

- Lead and managed multiple research projects studying how humans, animals and AI models learn in decision making and navigation tasks.
- Used **machine learning to study neural time series and behaviour data**, developed custom analysis pipelines and computational models to capture animal behaviour.
- Computational modelling for collaborative project with experimental neuroscience study on dopamine prediction errors, now under 2<sup>nd</sup> round review at Nature.
- Teaching assistant at UCL's Neural Computation course.
- Collaborated internationally with different academic and industry partners.
- Author for Dutch Review of Books, writing about AI and neuroscience.
- Mentored and supervised 2 PhD students.

#### PhD Researcher | Space & Memory Lab, UCL | September 2017 – March 2021

- Developed a **reinforcement model explaining contextual decision making** under uncertainty and hippocampal remapping, now published in Psych Review.
- Designed and implemented a novel reinforcement learning framework for **modelling spatial cognition**, now published in PNAS.

- Teaching assistant, developing and presenting course material for new courses in theoretical neuroscience and python programming at the SWC and Gatsby Unit.
- Organised internationally renowned neuroscience seminar series SWC Annual Symposium
- Volunteer teacher at BrainCamp Kosovo.
- **Published 2 peer-reviewed journal publications**, presented 8+ poster and talks at international conferences such as **ICLR**, **Cosyne** and **CCN**.

# Education

#### Ph.D. in Computational Neuroscience

University College London, 2021

Dissertation: "Hippocampal predictive maps of an uncertain world" Advisor: Neil Burgess | Examiners: Athena Akrami & Peter Dayan

M.Sc. in Brain and Mind Sciences

University College London & ENS Paris, 2016

Graduated with Distinction

B.Sc. in Natural Sciences & Neuroscience

University of Amsterdam, 2014

Graduated with Honors, minor in Philosophy & Ethics

## **Selected Publications**

- Geerts JP, Stachenfeld KLS, Chan SCY & Clopath C. "Determinants of emergent acquisition of transitive inference during in-context learning." in prep.
- Greenstreet FMJ\*, Geerts JP\*, Gallego JA & Clopath C. "Learned action embeddings explain striatal and cortical representations during motor learning." in prep.
- Geerts JP, Gershman SJ, Burgess N & Stachenfeld KLS, "A probabilistic successor representation for context-dependent prediction." Psychological Review, 2023. DOI
- Greenstreet FMJ, [...] Geerts JP [...] Stephenson-Jones, M "Action prediction error: a value-free dopaminergic teaching signal that drives stable learning." under 2<sup>nd</sup> round review at Nature. preprint.
- Geerts JP\*, Chersi F\*, Stachenfeld KLS & Burgess N. "A general model of hippocampal and dorsal striatal learning and decision making." PNAS, 2020. DOI
- Pinotsis, DA, Geerts JP, et al. "Linking canonical microcircuits and neuronal activity: Dynamic causal modelling of laminar recordings." NeuroImage, 2017. DOI